うがっ！
ほわたぁ～！
(沖田)いけぇ～！
(神楽)うおぉぉ!!
(神楽)ああっ！
(沖田)ああ…｡
柳生四天王が立ちはだかる｡
そして お妙を奪い返すため➡
(沖田)ﾌﾝ！
このときを待っていたぜ｡
(神楽)ぬうぅぅ…！
(西野)おっ…｡
(西野)たあいもない！ おっ？
＜新八:柳生 九兵衛の嫁にと
連れ去られた お妙を助けるべく➡
しかし 彼らの前に
柳生 九兵衛率いる➡
新八をはじめとする
万事屋の３人と➡
ﾜｰｯﾊｯﾊ！ 策士 策に溺れるとは
このことよ!!
近藤 率いる真選組の３人が
柳生家に立ち向かった｡
６対６のｻﾊﾞｲﾊﾞﾙｹﾞｰﾑで
柳生に挑むことになった＞
Kyubei Yagyu took Otae away.
In an effort to rescue her, the Odd Jobs trio, led by Shinpachi,
and three of the Shinsengumi, led by Kondo, challenged the Yagyu clan.
But, the Four Aces of the Yagyu clan and their leader, Kyubei Yagyu, stand in their way.
In order to take Otae back, they must take on the Yagyu in a six-on-six game of survival.
That was too easy!
Hmph.
I was waiting for that.
Now!
The strategist is beaten by his own strategy!
[Kagura and Okita together gave the Kodokan team a victory over Nishino.]
[The second match is between Hijikata and Kitaoji. A match between a mayo maniac and a ketchup freak.]
Okita-san...
(新八)沖田さん…｡
(近藤)なんてこった｡
My god...
総悟が… あの総悟が…｡
Sogo... Not Sogo...
ひどい… 完全に足が折られてる｡
This is terrible. It's snapped in two.
相討ち… いや 足が折られてから
倒したとは考えにくい｡
They must've struck simultaneously...
I can't see how he could've defeated this man on a broken leg.
たぶん この男を倒して
疲労していたところを誰かに…｡
He probably defeated him, and then when he was exhausted...
(近藤)ｳｿだっ！
It can't be!
There's no way Sogo would lose...
総悟が 総悟が負けるはずねえ!!
なぁ 総悟…｡
Right, Sogo?
お前は うちの道場でもよ
いちばん覚えが早くてよ…｡
You were the quickest study at our dojo.
あっという間に
みんな 追い抜いてよ…｡
You surpassed everyone in no time at all.
また ｵﾚのこと
おちょくってんだろ？
You're teasing me again, aren't you?
その手にはのらんぞ｡
I won't fall for that.
なあ！ 総悟!!
返事しろよ 総悟！
Right, Sogo?
Answer me, Sogo!
許せねえ…｡
They won't get away with this.
They won't get away with this! I swear!
絶対 許せねえ!!
ここまで やる必要あんのかよ!?
Was it necessary to go this far?!
皿割ったら
終わりじゃねえのかよ！
Wasn't it supposed to end once the plate was broken?!
Those bastards must enjoy...tormenting people!
ﾔﾂら 人をいたぶんのを
楽しんでるとしか思えねえ！
Their cell phone...
《ｹｰﾀｲ… ﾔﾂらの…？
もしかしたら
沖田さんをやったﾔﾂが➡
Maybe they left evidence of who did this to Okita-san...
証拠を残して…》
Dammit!
ﾁｸｼｮｰ！ いったい誰なんだ？
こんな ひどいﾏﾈをしたﾔﾂは!?
Who the hell did such a cruel thing?!
総悟… お前の仇は
絶対 ｵﾚがとってやる！
Sogo, I'll get revenge for you, I swear!
なっ 新八君！
うおぉっ!!
Right, Shinpachi-kun?
Dammit! Who did this to Okita-san?! I have no idea!
ﾁｷｼｮｰ！
沖田さんやったの誰だこらぁ!!
皆目 見当がつかねえよ！
見つけたらﾏｼﾞ ぶっ殺してやんよ!!
If I ever find out, I'm seriously going to kill the bastard!
おうよ！ 絶対見つけて
ぶっ殺してやんぜ！
Yeah! I'll kill the bastard, too!
ん？
つうか どうした？ その汗｡
Huh? Why're you perspiring?
なんか暑いな おい！
もっと ｸｰﾗｰきかせろ こらぁ！
It's hot in here. Turn on the air conditioner! Those dummies!
ﾎﾞｹがっ!!
Come on out! Where'd you go?! We're avenging Okita-san!
出てきやがれ！ どこ行った！
沖田さんの仇は ﾎﾞｸたちが討つ!!
あ… すみません お食事中｡
Forgive us. We didn't know you were having a meal.
間違えました｡
Wrong room.
What the hell are you doing?!
(２人)って 何やってんだ～!!
["People Who Are Picky About Food Are Also Picky About People, Too"]
Can't fight on an empty stomach.
(北大路)腹が減っては戦もできぬ｡
どうだ？ ｷｻﾏらも…｡
Care to join us?
I'm not eating a meal prepared by the enemy!
敵の作った料理なんて 食えるか!!
Hijikata-san, what're you doing relaxing and taking it easy?
土方さん ｱﾝﾀ 何のんびり
くつろいでんですか？
３人で ｿｲﾂ
やっちゃいましょうよ！
Let's have the three of us take him out!
(土方)おい ﾃﾒｴら
余計な手 出すなよ｡
Hey! Don't interfere.
Hijikata-san!
土方さん！
ｺｲﾂは ｵﾚのﾁｬｰﾊﾝだ｡
I'm eating fried rice.
ﾁｬｰﾊﾝかい？
ちょっとそれ…➡
You're having fried rice?!
Pass the ketchup, will you?
ｹﾁｬｯﾌﾟ取ってくれ｡
ん？ これか？
Hm, this?
おいおい 何だよ？ これ…｡
Hey, what's going on here?
緊張感もｸｿも
あったもんじゃないんですけど｡
There's no tension or anything here.
凡人には わかるまいよ｡
Ordinary people wouldn't understand.
The match has already begun.
すでに 勝負は
始まっているということに｡
武士とは ﾒｼの食べ方ひとつ
箸の持ち方ひとつでも➡
Samurai do things their own way, be it a meal or even how they hold their chopsticks.
自分の流儀でいくものだ｡
日常すべてが
己の精神を鍛える修行だ｡
Everything they do in their daily life is training for their spirit.
そうして 武士の強靭な
鉄の魂は 培われる｡
It is how a samurai builds a strong, iron-willed spirit.
土方 十四郎よ… ｷｻﾏにはあるか？
それだけのものが！
Toshiro Hijikata. Do you have that in you?
ｹﾁｬｯﾌﾟ！ ｵﾑﾗｲｽに
ｹﾁｬｯﾌﾟをあんなに！
おぇ～…｡
Ketchup! That much ketchup on your rice omelet?!
Let me say one thing.
ひとつ言っておこう｡
Everyone around me thinks I'm totally crazy for ketchup,
ｵﾚは 周囲から
生粋のｹﾁｬﾗｰと思われているが➡
実は ﾄﾏﾄの類が大の苦手で
見るだけで吐き気がする｡
but the truth is, I can't stand tomatoes.
Just looking at one makes me want to puke.
By eating what I detest in excess, I build up an unbendable strong spirit.
(北大路)嫌いなものを
過度に食することにより➡
折れない
屈強な精神を作りあげる｡
今では
苦手だったﾄﾏﾄも大好きになり➡
Now I've come to love the tomatoes that I once couldn't eat
ﾄﾏﾄに ｹﾁｬｯﾌﾟをかけて食すほど｡
and even eat my tomatoes with ketchup.
《それもう 修行になってねえよ｡
ただの不摂生》
That's not training. That's just plain unhealthy.
ｷｻﾏに こんなことが ﾏﾈできるか？
Could you do what I did?
な… 何だ？ その白いのは…｡
Wh-What is that white stuff?!
ﾏﾖﾈｰｽﾞ｡
Mayonnaise!
《ま ﾏﾖﾈｰｽﾞ… ﾁｬｰﾊﾝにﾏﾖﾈｰｽﾞ？
M-Mayonnaise...
Mayonnaise on fried rice?! They don't go together!
そんなもの合うわけ…｡
…まさか ｺｲﾂも》
Could he also be...?
Let me say one thing.
ちなみに ひとつ言っておこう｡
Everyone around me thinks I'm a total mayo maniac,
ｵﾚは 周囲から
生粋のﾏﾖﾗｰと思われているが➡
実は ﾏﾖの類が大嫌いで➡
but the truth is, I can't stand mayonnaise.
あの 赤いｷｬｯﾌﾟを見るだけで
吐き気がする｡
Just seeing that red cap makes me want to puke.
[Note: Japanese mayo comes in a plastic squeeze bottle with a red cap.]
《ｳｿついてる》
《負けたくないばっかりに➡
He's lying!
He's lying through his teeth because he doesn't want to lose!
平気で ｳｿついたよ ﾏﾖﾗｰ》
That mayo maniac!
ﾌﾝ… だてに｢鬼の副長｣と➡
Hmph.
I see they don't call you the Demon Vice-Chief for nothing.
呼ばれているわけでは
ないようだな｡
なかなか おもしろい食事だった｡
That was quite an interesting meal.
I need a smoke. Do you have an ashtray?
ﾀﾊﾞｺ 吸いてえな… 灰皿 あるか？
Where's your thanks for the meal before you smoke?
ﾀﾊﾞｺの前に
ごちそうさま は どうした？
ｸｿまずいﾒｼ ごちそうさんでした｡
Thanks for the god-awful meal.
ほら… 灰皿だ！
Here...
Your ashtray!
♪♪～
ほう… 想像以上の反応だ｡
You have faster reflexes than I expected.
並外れた身体能力… 反射神経｡
You possess exceptional physical skills...reflexes...
数多の死線をくぐり抜け
培った勘と度胸｡
Intuition and courage nurtured by surviving numerous close calls with death.
(北大路)実戦剣術とは
よくいったもの…｡
Fight-tested sword skills indeed.
並大抵の剣客では かなうまい｡
Most ordinary swordsmen would be no match for you.
だが そんな戦い方が
通じるのは 三流まで｡
But that fighting style only works on third-rate swordsmen.
達人同士の勝負においては
通用せん｡
It won't work in a duel between two masters.
ﾃﾒｴが 達人だって？
You? A master?
虫も殺したことねえような
ﾂﾗしやがって ﾎﾞﾝﾎﾞﾝが｡
You look like you've never even killed a bug in your life, sonny.
殺し合いだけが剣術ではないぞ｡
Killing each other is not all there is to swordsmanship.
かかってこい！
Bring it on!
…ぬかしやがれ！
You're...all talk!
I know what you're going to do.
ｷｻﾏの手は 読めているぞ｡
あえて大技で隙を作り 敵を誘い➡
You use a head-on attack that leaves you open for your enemy to attack.
打ち込んできたところを
その 持ち前の勘で➡
And when he does, you use your quick instincts to parry the blow.
とらえて さばく…｡
I can read...your moves as well!
ﾃﾒｴの動きも 読めてんだよ！
勘がよすぎるんだよ… ｷｻﾏは｡
Your instincts are too sharp.
♪♪～
Toshi!
(近藤)ﾄｼ！
You twisted your body to protect the plate from the blow.
体をひねって
皿への直撃を避けたか｡
Your instincts are truly impressive.
本当に たいした直感力だ｡
しかし それが ｷｻﾏの命取り｡
But that will be your demise.
This is bad. That man figured out Toshi's habits in such a short time.
まずい… あの男 ﾄｼの癖を
この短時間で見抜いた｡
(近藤)ｵﾚたち 真選組の
得意とする➡
In the real-sword fighting style that we Shinsengumi are proud of,
真剣での立ち合いにおいて➡
taking a single blow from an opponent means certain death.
相手のひと太刀を受けることは
死に直結する｡
ゆえに ｵﾚたちに
絶対的に求められるのは➡
That's why the ability to sense danger is an absolute requirement.
危機察知能力｡
研ぎ澄まされた直感力で
相手の気配を察知し➡
The ability to sense your opponent's movements using a highly honed intuition...
敵の攻めを制す｡
to stop the enemy's attack.
ﾄｼは 誰よりも その能力に長ける｡
Toshi is better at that than anyone.
だが 野郎の得意とする
道場剣術は➡
But this guy's dojo swordsmanship
敵を斬るよりも 意表をつき
一本とる術に長けたもの｡
excels at surprise attacks to score points rather than killing blows.
ﾔﾂの前では ﾄｼの尋常ならざる
勘のよさは仇になる｡
Versus this guy, Toshi's exceptional instincts work against him.
あの でけえ皿だ… いつもより
過敏に反応せざるをえねえ｡
Carrying that huge plate, he's forced to react quicker than usual.
ﾔﾂは そんなﾄｼの隙をついてくる｡
That guy will attack Toshi's openings.
攻めると見せかけ 引き➡
He'll feign an attack and back off.
Act like he's backing away,
引くと見せかけ 攻める！
then strike.
♪♪～
(近藤)無数の疑餌を
無意識で反応してしまう➡
Toshi will unconsciously react... to that guy's countless feints.
ｷﾞﾘｷﾞﾘのﾚﾍﾞﾙで 繰り出してくる｡
紛うことなき達人｡
That guy will do it over and over again.
He is unmistakably a master.
His is a dojo sword style that can bend the minds of others to his will.
(近藤)人の心 己の心さえ
自在に操る道場剣術…｡
If this were a dojo match, I'd have already scored multiple times.
道場試合であれば
もう何本とったことか｡
いや ｷｻﾏの得意な実戦であっても
すでに命はないだろう｡
And if this were a real fight, you'd have already lost your life.
いいかげん あきらめろ…｡
Give it up already.
そんな でかい皿では
防戦一方だろう｡
You'll be stuck on the defensive with that huge plate.
♪♪～
You still want to continue?
まだ やるのか？
A point, two points...it doesn't matter how many you get-it's all irrelevant!
１本だ ２本だ んなもん
何本取られようが 関係ねえよ｡
腕１本 もげようが
足１本 取られようが➡
A fight with real swords means you have to keep fighting even if you lose an arm or a leg.
首つながってる限り
戦わなきゃならねえのが➡
Just so long as your head is still attached.
真剣勝負ってもんだ｡
This is why I detest the barbaric country samurai fighting style...
これだから…
野蛮な芋流派は ｲﾔになる｡
そういや 灰皿 借りたぜ…｡
By the way, I borrowed an ashtray.
ﾀﾊﾞｺ吸わねえと 調子出ねえんだ｡
I can't get going without a smoke.
《ｵﾚの皿…！》
Is that my plate?!
Damn you, when did you...
ｷｻﾏ いったい いつ…！
When?!
♪♪～
Huh? I still have it.
《あれ？ ある…》
《あれは… あのときの！》
That's...from earlier...
擬餌だか なんだか知らねえが➡
I don't know if you'd call that a feint,
だまくらかし合いなら
負けねえよ｡
but I won't lose to you when it comes to deception.
♪♪～
For all the ketchup you poured on your rice omelet,
ｵﾑﾗｲｽに いくら
ｹﾁｬｯﾌﾟをかけようが➡
常識の範囲内！
you kept it to a reasonable amount.
You're unable to break away from your set forms.
ﾃﾒｴは しょせん
型から脱しきれてねえ｡
ｿｲﾂが 道場剣術の限界よ｡
That's the limitation of dojo swordsmanship.
ｵﾚぁ ﾃﾞｻﾞｰﾄにだってﾏﾖﾈｰｽﾞをかける｡
I put mayonnaise even on dessert.
こいよ… 本物のｹﾝｶ 見せてやる｡
Come. I'll show you what real fighting is.
♪♪～
Fights, real battles...
ｹﾝｶだ 実戦だ そんなことを
声高に叫び➡
In my time, I've seen many like yourself who shout such words
道場稽古を軽んずる
ｷｻﾏのような輩を➡
and make light of dojo practice.
ｵﾚは今まで たくさん見てきた｡
試合では負けたが
我が流派は実戦向きです｡
They lose the match,
but claim their swordsmanship is more suited to actual battle.
真剣勝負なら負けません…
すべて ただの言い訳だ｡
They claim they wouldn't lose if it had been with real swords.
Those are all excuses.
そんな戯言は 稽古もろくにせん
根性なしの言い草｡
That drivel is what people who don't practice say.
もう聞き飽きた｡
I've heard enough.
No matter how much natural ability you have,
どれだけ才能があろうと
どれだけ実戦を踏もうと➡
no matter how many times you've been in a real fight,
努力した者には勝てん｡
you cannot win against someone who trains everyday.
ｵﾚは そう思っている｡
That's what I believe.
古い考え方などという輩も
いるがな｡
But, there are some who believe my thinking is old-fashioned.
《近藤:古いよ… ﾃﾞﾌｫﾙﾒが古い》
It's old, all right. And so it that deformity.
今 ｵﾚの目を見て古いとか
思ったﾔﾂが いちばん古い｡
Anyone who thinks my deformity is old-fashioned is really the old-fashioned ones.
《近藤:いや お前のが古い》
No, yours is beyond old.
Hey, what's with your eyes?
Why do they look like butts?
(土方)おい どういうことだ？
その目は｡
(土方)なんで ｹﾂがついてんだ？
You're more rude than old-fashioned.
《近藤:お前は 古い以前にﾊﾞｶ》
While you were wildly swinging your swords around screaming about fights and real battles,
ｷｻﾏらがｹﾝｶだ 実戦だと
闇雲に剣を振り回す間➡
ｵﾚたちは 必死に稽古を積み
努力をしてきたんだ｡
we were doing everything we could to train ourselves.
ｷｻﾏは ｵﾚに勝てん｡
You people cannot win against us.
No, no, you're certainly deadly with words. Now, let's try swords.
いやいや 口ｹﾞﾝｶは
なかなかに達者じゃねえか！
今度は こっちでやろうぜ！
たわけが！ 思い知るがいい…｡
(土方)うおぉ!!
Fool! Learn your lesson!
Hmph.
ﾌｯ… 相も変わらぬ一辺倒な剣筋｡
Your attack pattern never changes.
(北大路)
どんなに攻め込んでこようと…｡
No matter how many times you attack
《北大路:そのでかい皿を
背負うかぎり➡
as long as you carry that huge plate, you'll always have to be on the defensive.
ｷｻﾏは 後手に回らざるをえない｡
ｵﾚが 皿に
打ち込む気配をみせれば➡
If I show any sign of striking at that plate, you'll always switch to the defensive.
必ずｷｻﾏは 守りに転ずる｡
たとえ それが
ｵﾚの擬餌とわかっていても➡
Even if you know I'm feinting, you'll bite. That will leave you open.
食いついてくる｡
そこに ｽｷが生まれる｡
Here's the bait. Bite.
さぁ ｴｻだ！ 食いつけ!!
ｻﾞｺめが！》
You're just a small fry!
うぅっ…｡
What?
I'm sick of your cheap bait.
安いｴｻは もう食い飽きたぜ｡
ｵﾚを釣り上げてえなら➡
If you want to land this fish, bring me a full course meal smothered in mayonnaise.
ﾌﾙｺｰｽに ﾏﾖﾈｰｽﾞぶっかけて
持ってきな！
四の五の考えるのは もうやめだ！
No more fishing me out!
もう 後手には回らねえ！
I won't...retreat anymore!
《擬餌ごと巻き込む連撃！》
A high-speed attack to counter the feints.
His plan is to mount a ferocious attack so his enemy has no time to counter-attack.
猛攻をかけ よけいな小技すら
出す暇を与えないつもりか！
攻撃こそ最大の防御｡
Offense is the best defense. He's finally acting like himself.
ようやく
ﾔﾂらしくなってきやがった！
一気にｶﾀをつけるつもりか！
I see you're trying to finish this.
だが このような足場で
ﾑﾘに攻勢に出ても➡
But you can't launch a decisive attack in a place with such poor footing.
動きは制約され
体力は消耗するだけ｡
Your movement is hampered, so you'll just exhaust yourself.
What's more, you have a fatal weakness.
くわえてｷｻﾏには
致命的な弱点がある！
ぬかせ～！
Don't give me that!
(北大路)ｵﾚには ｷｻﾏの剣筋が
手にとるように読める｡
I can read your moves like a book.
勢いに任せるのみで
変化のない単純な剣撃｡
Monotonous brute force strikes that never change.
いくら打ち込んできたところで➡
No matter how many times you swing, you won't be able to hit me even once.
ｵﾚに
ひと太刀浴びせるのは ﾑﾘな話｡
(土方)剣筋は読めても…｡
うっ！
You may be able to read my sword...
But you can you read my feet underwater?!
水中の足の動きは
読めねえだろう！
ｷｻﾏは ｵﾚを
型にはまっていると言った｡
You said I'm stuck in my set forms,
ｵﾚから見れば ｷｻﾏも
十分 型にはまっている！
but from what I can see, you're the one stuck in set forms.
ｵﾚたちは あらゆる型を
幾千 幾万も 体に たたき込み➡
Thousands, tens of thousands of patterns and counters have been hammered into my body.
その対応策も知っている！
I have learned every possible set form.
♪♪～
It's more reliable than the simple intuition and instinct you rely on.
それは ｷｻﾏが頼りとする
勘や直感よりも確かなもの｡
やり合えば そこには
一瞬の判断の差が生まれる｡
In a duel, it manifests as a split-second difference in decision-making.
うおぉ～！
達人同士の立ち合いにおいて➡
In a duel between masters, that difference becomes fatal!
その差は致命的なものとなる｡
それが ｷｻﾏとｵﾚの差…｡
This is the difference between you and me.
才能におぼれ
努力を怠ったｷｻﾏの敗因！
Neglecting to work hard because you were too full of your own natural ability will be your downfall!
This is the strength of the dojo swordsmanship...that you mocked!
これが お前が揶揄した
道場剣術の力よ！
うっ…｡
Oh no!
やばい！ あの人
本当に とんでもなく強い!!
That guy is insanely strong! Kondo-san, let's help him!
近藤さん 助けに入りましょう！
近藤さん！
すまん…｡
Kondo-san!
Sorry. Please don't assist him.
手は出さんでやってくれ｡
えっ？
What...?
お妙さんの身がかかってる
戦いで➡
It's hard to hold back when Otae-san is at stake,
言えた義理じゃねえが➡
but he hates to lose more than anyone.
あれは 人一倍 負けず嫌いだ…
手を出したら殺される｡
If you interfere, he'll kill you.
You say he hates to lose, but if this continues, he'll lose anyway!
負けず嫌いって このままじゃ
土方さん 負けますよ！
そうかもしれん…
しかし ﾄｼに加勢することは➡
Maybe so.
But if we assist Toshi, it will mean that I didn't trust him.
ｵﾚがｱｲﾂを信じないということだ｡
He knows better than anyone that street style sword fighting won't defeat that guy.
ただのｹﾝｶ剣法じゃ
あれには勝てねえのは➡
ｱｲﾂが いちばん知ってるさ｡
(近藤)なぁ ﾄｼよ…｡
Right, Toshi?
昔な まだ
ｵﾚたちが江戸に出てくる前➡
It happened a long time ago, before we came to Edo,
田舎で ｵﾚが
剣術道場やってる頃の話だ｡
when I was still training in our dojo out in the country.
巷を騒がす
とんでもねえ悪ｶﾞｷがいてな…｡
There was a young thug who went around making a lot of trouble.
めっぽうｹﾝｶの強え 一匹狼で➡
He was a loner with excellent fighting skills.
近隣の道場に
片っ端からｹﾝｶ売って➡
A delinquent who went looking for fights at all the dojos in the area and beat them up.
しばき回してる暴れん坊よ｡
(近藤)
田舎道場の連中なんざ みんな➡
The guys at country dojos are all hot-blooded punks.
血の気の多い
ﾁﾝﾋﾟﾗみてえなﾔﾂらばかりだ｡
これじゃあ
ﾒﾝﾂが立たねえってんで➡
They were losing face and decided to join together to beat the guy up.
みんなで 協力して ｿｲﾂを
やっちまおうって話になったんだ｡
ﾔﾂら １対１の武士道なんて
持ち合わせちゃいねえ…｡
They had no Bushido honor of fighting one-on-one.
Anyway, the kid deserved it. So I went to watch.
まぁ 自業自得だがな｡
ｵﾚも 物見遊山で見に行ったんだ｡
(近藤)そしたら ｺｲﾂが
なかなか ふてえ野郎でな…｡
Turns out the kid had balls.
大人数を前にしても
物怖じひとつせず➡
Even against large numbers, he wasn't a bit intimidated.
詫び入れるどころか たった一人で
多勢相手に大立ち回り➡
Instead of apologizing,
he went on a rampage against the large group, taking down one after another.
ﾊﾞｯﾀﾊﾞｯﾀ 敵をなぎ倒し
いやぁ 強えのなんの…｡
Damn was he strong.
(近藤)まぁ でも あの人数相手に
勝てるわきゃねえ！
But there was no way he could win against such numbers.
最後の最後
ぼろぞうきんみてえになるまで➡
In the end, he kept fighting until he was beaten to a pulp.
暴れ続けてたがな…｡
(近藤)ｵﾚは どうしたもんか
迷ったが➡
I debated what to do and then decided to bring him back to my dojo.
ｿｲﾂを道場に
連れて帰ることにした｡
そのまま捨て置けば
死んじまいそうだったし➡
He looked like he would've died If I left him there
何より
おもしろそうな男だったんでな｡
and he seemed like an interesting fellow.
333! 334!
((近藤:333！ 334！
(近藤)ぬぉ～っ!!
もう ﾀﾞﾒ！ もう 限界！
I can't do any more. That's my limit. My arms are gonna fall off.
腕が もげる～!!
Don't give up so easily!
(祖父)甘ったれたこと
言ってんじゃねえ！
At this rate, I'll never be able to pass on the dojo to you!
そんなんじゃ いつまでたっても
道場 任せらんねえぞ！
I'll probably die soon. What'll you do then?
もうすぐ ﾜｼ 死ぬぜ たぶん｡
どうすんの！
What's the point of swinging this heavy log?
こんな 丸太 素振りして
意味あんのかよ～！
もう 手が 血豆だらけなんだよ！
My hands are covered with blood blisters!
Swordsmanship is not about technique. It's about attitude, fool!
剣術は 技じゃねえ｡
気組みじゃ ﾎﾞｹ～!!
Swinging that log improves your sword skill and strengthens your character!
こんだけのものを振ってれば
しぜん 筋も違ってくる！
It grounds you!
根も 植えつけられる！
小手先で 振るな～！
Don't swing with your hands.
Discipline your breathing and swing with your entire body!
呼吸を練って てごと さばけ～!!
(沖田)ﾌﾝｯ！ ﾌﾝｯ！ ﾌﾝｯ…！
Look at Sogo.
(祖父)総悟を 見ろ～｡
あんなに 小さいのに➡
He's so tiny, but he's swinging that thick log. Isn't he amazing?
あんなに 太いの振り回してんぞ｡
すごくね～？
(祖父)やっぱ すげえな ｵﾒｴ｡
ﾜｼが 見込んだだけ あるわ｡
You are amazing. I knew you had it in you. You are a prodigy.
神童だよ 神童｡ んっ？
Huh? Is this peeling?
(祖父)あれ？ 何か めくれてね？
ってか これ
ただの 木の皮じゃねえ？
This is nothing but tree bark.
Good grief. This is why nobody wants to train here.
ったく｡ これだから ｳﾁには➡
いつまでたっても
門人が 集まんねえんだ｡ んっ？
Huh?
どうだ？ お前も｡
Give it a try?
Maybe not. Not with those injuries.
まだ ﾑﾘか｡ そのｹｶﾞじゃ｡
From what I can tell, you're blessed with natural talent.
ｵﾚの見たところ
お前には 天賦の才がある｡
どこで 習ったわけでもねえのに➡
You haven't studied under anyone, but your movements and instinct are extraordinary.
体裁きといい 機転といい
並々ならねえ｡
(近藤)だが 才だけでは 勝てねえ｡
But you can't win on talent alone.
(近藤)結局
努力してるﾔﾂには 勝てんぞ｡
In the end, it's the guy who works hard that wins.
(土方)興味ねえなぁ｡
Not interested.
(土方)丸太 振って 強くなれりゃ
わけねえんだよ｡
Nobody becomes a great swordsman by playing with lumber.
しょせん ただの喧嘩屋か…))
He's just a punk, after all.
But despite his words, he stayed.
(近藤)そのくせ その男は
そこから 動かなかった｡
He watched us train like a hungry wolf watching a herd of bacon-wrapped sheep.
(近藤)いつも そこで
ｵﾚたちの稽古を➡
噛みつきそうな目で 見ていた｡
But one day, even though his wounds hadn't fully healed, he disappeared from the dojo.
(近藤)だが ある日
傷も癒えてねえってのに➡
野郎
道場から 姿 消しやがってな｡
I was worried and went looking for him.
(近藤)心配して
捜しにいったら…｡
Move, you!
((ﾁﾝﾋﾟﾗ:そこ どけ ｺﾗ～！
We're on our way to raid the Kondo dojo!
(ﾁﾝﾋﾟﾗ)ｵﾚたちは 今から
近藤んとこの道場に➡
殴り込みに 行くんだよ！
We heard they were sheltering you!
(ﾁﾝﾋﾟﾗ)野郎 ﾃﾒｴを
かくまってたらしいじゃねえか｡
いったい どういうつもりだ!?
Why'd they do that?!
That's why I left. They're not involved anymore. Leave them alone.
(土方)だから 今 出てきたって
言ってんだろう｡
(土方)ﾔﾂは もう 関係ねえ｡
手え 出すな｡
You may have nothing to do with them, but we still do!
(ﾁﾝﾋﾟﾗ)ｵﾒｴに 関係なくても
こっちには あんだよ！
近藤やる前に また ﾃﾒｴ
ぶちのめしてやろうか！ あん!!
Before we beat up the Kondos, we'll kick the crap out of you!
(ﾁﾝﾋﾟﾗ)えっ!?))
♪♪～
He had become stronger than before.
(近藤)野郎は
以前より 強くなっていた｡
(近藤)ｹｶﾞが
癒えてねえのにも かかわらず➡
Despite his injuries,
he possessed a solid framework to his form that hadn't been there before.
その動きには 以前にはない
しっかりした骨格が できていた｡
だが ﾔﾂの戦いを見てられたのも
そこまで…｡
I couldn't just stand by and watch.
((土方:ﾊｧ ﾊｧ ﾊｧ…))
In the end, he and I were the only ones left standing.
(近藤)気がつきゃ 周りは 血の海｡
Surrounded by our defeated enemies.
(近藤)立ってんのは
ｵﾚと野郎だけだった｡
Why're you here?
((なんで いるんだ？ お前…｡
You can't use our sword style to act like a ruffian.
ｳﾁの流派の剣を➡
私情の戦いに 使ってもらっては
困る！
When did I ever join your school? And besides, you did a lot of fighting yourself.
(土方)ｵﾚが いつ
お前の流派に 入ったよ！
(土方)だいたい お前も
さんざん 暴れ回ってただろうが！
ったく お人好しだか
なんだか知らねえが➡
For crying out loud, What are you, some sort of good Samaritan?
借りを返すつもりが
また 借り 作っちまったよ…｡
I was trying to return your favor, but now I owe you again.
借りなんて 思わんでいい！
You don't owe me anything.
Come back and visit us anytime. You're already one of our students.
また いつでも 遊びに来い！
もう お前は ｳﾁの門弟だ！
Like I said before-when did I ever join your school?
(土方)だから いつ ｵﾚが
お前の流派に 入ったってんだよ！
ﾌｯ！ その 手のひら…
ｿｲﾂが その印だ！
Those hands...
Are the proof.
How many times did you swing it? Even I didn't get that many blisters.
何回 振った？ ｵﾚでも そこまで
血豆は できんかったぞ！
No wonder your injuries were slow to heal.
(近藤)どうりで 傷の治りが
遅いはずだ～！
These aren't blisters.
(土方)血豆じゃねえ！
四越ﾃﾞﾊﾟｰﾄの自動ﾄﾞｱに 挟まった))
My hand got caught in the automatic door of the Yotsukoshi Department Store.
[Note: Parody of Mitsukoshi Department Store.]
♪♪～
That's who Toshiro Hijikata is.
(近藤)それが
土方 十四郎という男だ｡
He never expresses his feelings to anyone.
(近藤)人には 決して見せねえ｡
And he never shows it on his face.
(近藤)ﾂﾗにも 毛程も出さねえ｡
だが ｵﾚは 知ってるよ｡
But I know...
Back then, and now...
野郎は 今も昔も➡
The only thing he cares about is sword fighting.
頭には 剣のことしかねえ｡
He's hiding his sword underwater so I can't read where it's coming from.
《水中に 剣を隠して
軌道を 読ませぬつもりか…》
こざかしい！
今さら そんなものが通じるか!!
Nice try!
Do you think that'll work on me now?!
誰にも 努力してねえ なんて
言わせねえ！
No one trains harder than him.
Certainly,
そりゃあ 確かに
柳生の 華麗な剣に比べりゃ➡
compared to the showy sword style of the Yagyu,
it might be a rough and unpolished country style, but...
武骨で いびつな
野刀かもしれねえ！
だが…
研ぎ澄まされた ﾔﾂの剣は…！
his sharply honed sword skills...
♪♪～
can slice through steel!
(近藤)鉄をも 切り裂く!!
あっ…！
Hijikata-san!
土方さん!!
待たせたな｡
Sorry for the wait.
ﾌｯ！ ﾄｼ…
また 派手に やられたもんだな！
Toshi, you got beaten by him pretty badly this time.
あん？
Huh? These aren't from that guy.
(土方)これは
ﾔﾂに やられたんじゃねえ｡
間留井ﾃﾞﾊﾟｰﾄの自動ﾄﾞｱに 挟まった｡
I got caught in the automatic door of the Marui Department Store.
[Note: Parody of OIOI Department Store.]
So Nishino and Kitaoji are both out?
I wasn't expecting the enemy to do this well.
I miscalculated a bit.
I thought with Kitaoji there, the three of you would be enough...
Now there are five of them, and we're already down to three...
Tojo-san, we have four. I'm still in.
One of the Four Aces: Sui Minamito.
I got caught off guard and they roughed me up a bit,
but the plate is still intact.
Please give me another chance to make up for it.
Oh, that's right. Then...
Now there are three.
Having someone like you around would only disgrace the name of the dojo.
I, Ayumu Tojo, head of the Four Yagyu Aces will not forgive anyone
who tarnishes our Young Lord's name.
The next episode ... "Four Heads are Better than One."
[Tojo ruthlessly eliminated Minamito. Kyubei finally joins the battle!]
(東城)ほぅ～｡
西野と北大路が おちましたか｡
[Meanwhile, Gintoki and Kondo are engaged in an epic struggle.]
敵が ここまで やるとは
少々 読みを誤りましたね｡
(東城)北大路が いれば
あなた方 ３人でも➡
事足りると思ったのですが…｡
これで 敵は ５人｡
こちらは すでに ３人にまで
なってしまいましたか…｡
(南戸)東城さん ４人だ！
まだ ｵﾚが いる！
柳生四天王が一 南戸粋が！
油断して 少々 やられたが
皿は 無事だ｡
もういっぺん
挽回する機会を くれ！
あぁ そうでしたか｡ じゃあ…｡
ぐぉ～っ!!
これで ３人ですね｡
あなたのような者が
いたところで➡
柳生流の看板に 傷が つくだけ｡
若の御名を けなす者は
誰だろうと➡
この 柳生四天王筆頭➡
東城 歩が 許しません｡